<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three Suggestions for Serving Scallops</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="504859"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HODGSON, MOIRA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC1439F931A35751C0A964958260" item-length="870" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three Suggestions for Serving Scallops</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOIRA HODGSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HODGSON, MOIRA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEEING sparkling fresh by J.P. bay scallops in the market recently reminded me of the time I harvested them in Nantucket in the middle of winter. Dressed in boots, orange waders and hooded slickers, we went out on the bay early one rainy morning in a tiny wooden boat. We caught the scallops in dredges made of metal frames interwoven with string and iron rings, which scraped along the bay floor, dragging up the scallops and whatever else was down there.</p>
        <p>The scallop hops along the sea floor by snapping together its two shells like a castanet, squirting water through membranes between the fluted edges of the shells. The water is propelled by a single muscle, which connects the shells and opens them and closes them. The muscle is the part we eat (in Europe, the roe, which is bigger than the roe of our scallops, is eaten, too, and the scallops are sold in their shells).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEEING sparkling fresh bay scallops in the market recently reminded me of the time I harvested them in Nantucket in the middle of winter. Dressed in boots, orange waders and hooded slickers, we went out on the bay early one rainy morning in a tiny wooden boat. We caught the scallops in dredges made of metal frames interwoven with string and iron rings, which scraped along the bay floor, dragging up the scallops and whatever else was down there.</p>
        <p>The scallop hops along the sea floor by snapping together its two shells like a castanet, squirting water through membranes between the fluted edges of the shells. The water is propelled by a single muscle, which connects the shells and opens them and closes them. The muscle is the part we eat (in Europe, the roe, which is bigger than the roe of our scallops, is eaten, too, and the scallops are sold in their shells).</p>
        <p>After we had sorted through the two bushels that we brought to shore, we set about shucking the scallops. This is a disconcerting experience once you learn that each scallop has about 30 eyes. They are only the size of pinheads, but they have a cornea, lens and an optic nerve -- and they are bright blue.</p>
        <p>Sea and bay scallops can be used interchangeably in most recipes, but the flavor of sea scallops is not as delicate as those from the bay, and they are much larger. All scallops exude a lot of juice when they are cooked. Cook them as little as possible, or they will become tough.</p>
        <p>The following recipe is inspired by a dish from the French chef Alain Senderens. A full-bodied dry white wine goes well with it. Steamed Scallops With Fennel and Ricard</p>
        <p>Total time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon unsalted butter  2 medium bulbs fennel, sliced thin  Coarse salt and freshly ground pepper to taste  3/4 teaspoon curry powder  1/2 cup water  1 pound bay scallops  1 tablespoon chopped dill  2 tablespoons Ricard or Pernod (or other anise-flavored alcohol).</p>
        <p>1. Melt butter in a saute pan over moderate heat. Add fennel, season with salt, pepper and curry powder, stir and then add just enough water almost to cover (about half a cup). Simmer gently for 15 minutes, adding a little more water if necessary to keep it from drying out. When fennel is cooked lift it out of the pan with slotted spoon and place it on a serving platter. Keep warm while making the sauce.</p>
        <p>2. Place scallops on half of a large sheet of aluminum foil. Season with salt, pepper, dill and the Ricard or Pernod. Fold the other half of the foil over scallops, and roll the edges together, pressing on them to seal the scallops inside.</p>
        <p>3. Bring some water to a boil in the bottom of a steamer (or a large pot with a steaming basket set in it). Place the scallops in the basket, cover the pot and steam for nine minutes.</p>
        <p>4. When the scallops are cooked, remove from steamer and place on plate. Open the foil package carefully and place scallops on the bed of fennel. Whisk the cooking juices from the scallops into the sauce. Reduce until thickened, pour over scallops and serve. Sauteed Bay Scallops In Orange Sauce</p>
        <p>Total time: 15 minutes</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons olive oil  Flour for dredging  1 pound bay scallops  Coarse salt and freshly ground pepper to taste  1 clove garlic, chopped fine  1/2 cup fresh orange juice</p>
        <p>4 tablespoons chopped parsley  1 tablespoon orange peel, blanched and cut in julienne.</p>
        <p>1. Heat oil in a large nonstick frying pan over high heat. Dredge the scallops lightly with flour, shaking off excess.</p>
        <p>2. Saute the scallops, shaking the pan and stirring so they cook evenly, for three minutes. Season to taste with salt and pepper.</p>
        <p>3. Add garlic and saute for two minutes. Add the orange juice, the parsley and the orange peel. Cook for about 30 seconds, enough to thicken the sauce. Correct the seasoning and serve immediately.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings. Sauteed Scallops With Artichokes</p>
        <p>Total time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>6 tablespoons olive oil  1 garlic clove, crushed  2 large artichoke hearts, sliced or 8 to 10 baby artichokes, trimmed and sliced.  Coarse salt and freshly ground pepper to taste  1/4 cup chopped parsley  2 pounds bay scallops, rinsed and patted dry  Flour for dredging.</p>
        <p>1. In a heavy skillet, heat three tablespoons of oil over medium heat. Add garlic, let it cook for 30 seconds, and discard it. Add artichoke slices, season with salt and pepper, and cook stirring frequently until they are tender -- about 10 to 12 minutes. Add parsley and cook for a minute more. Remove artichoke mixture from the skillet and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Heat remaining oil in skillet over medium heat. Season scallops with salt and pepper, lightly dredge them in flour and shake them in a sieve to remove excess flour. Add them to the skillet and cook them, tossing constantly, until they are firm and opaque -- about three minutes.</p>
        <p>3. Using a slotted spoon, remove scallops to a heated serving dish and keep them warm. Pour off oil in the pan, heat the artichoke slices and garnish the scallops with them.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Note: This is adapted from "The Harry's Bar Cookbook" by Arrigo Cipriani, Bantam Books, 1991.</p>
        <p>ILS&gt;Drawing  FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
